Finding Aid for Medical School Sesquicentennial Office (University of Michigan) records, 1997-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Medical School Sesquicentennial Office (University of Michigan) records 1997-2000
University of Michigan. Medical School Sesquicentennial Office.
1 oversize folders
2 linear feet
0252 Bimu C46 2
Office established to plan and coordinate events, exhibits, and publicity for the University of Michigan Medical School sesquicentennial. Records include committee minutes, event schedules and planning material, press releases, clippings, articles, publicity, script and production files for sesquicentennial video, and student life photographs. Also includes videotape and audio tape of media coverage of events and lapel pins and merchandise created for the sesquicentennial.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was transferred by the University of Michigan Medical School Sesquicentennial Office (Donor no. 647 ) in January 2001.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open for research.
The University of Michigan Medical School was founded in 1848 and graduated its first class in 1850. The school celebrated its centennial in 1950, so in March 1997, the dean of the Medical School, Lorris Betz, began planning a sesquicentennial celebration for the Medical School for the year 2000. An administrative committee created a plan for the celebration and created an office to coordinate the celebration. The plan, approved in March 1998 included the publication of a book and video, exhibits and displays for the University of Michigan community and the Medical Center, departmental events, a symposium, regional meetings, and a variety of ceremonies and celebrations, beginning with a convocation ceremony in October 1999, through a gala final celebration in October 2000. Allen S. Lichter continued the plans when he became dean in December, 1998.
The Sesquicentennial office operated from 1998 until the end of 2000, and oversaw the implementation of the sesquicentennial plan and publicity. Staff of the sesquicentennial office included head coordinator Kate Schuch, Linda Diebold, Deborah Grifka and consultant Jean Horrigan. A sesquicentennial committee was formed of doctors from each of the departments, representatives from the Medical School dean's office, the Medical Center Alumni and Development Office, the Historical Center for the Health Sciences, and the sesquicentennial staff, chaired by Robert Bartlett. The committee met from 1998 through 2000 to coordinate the sesquicentennial celebrations.
The committee hired a public relations firm, Franco Public Relations, to coordinate a national publicity campaign for print, radio and television. Recognition was received from a number of sources. The Medical School Sesquicentennial was noted in the United States Congressional Record, was the subject of a Journal of the American Medical Association issue, as well as numerous articles published in local and national newspapers and magazines. Segments about the sesquicentennial were aired on the NBC Today Show and Detroit Radio WJR-AM station's morning show in February 2000. A logo design for the sesquicentennial was created and used for stationery, stickers, invitations, brochures, and a variety of merchandise.
A number of exhibits and displays were created for the sesquicentennial. A time line of accomplishments was created as a poster and displayed on the sesquicentennial web site. Alumni were asked for memories, and their letters created a "Memory Lane" display, both within the medical center and on the web site. The Medical Center also had a variety of displays within the buildings, including class photograph displays, alumni hall of honor, a display of an iron lung machine, a display of antique surgeons' tools and a turn-of-the-century doctor's office. The University Art Museum also held an exhibition titled Seeing is Healing, The Visual Arts of Medicine. Historical Markers were designed and placed around the campus where the original medical buildings once stood.
A number of large events were planned for the sesquicentennial year. The kickoff event, a convocation in October 1999, was held at the same time as an all-alumni reunion. The convocation brought together distinguished alumni speakers and paid tribute to the Medical School's history. A symposium, speakers, and small events celebrated the sesquicentennial until the finale week which included a Medical Center birthday party luncheon, and a gala dinner to close the year's events.
In addition, a video was created to publicize the history of the Medical School with narration by University of Michigan alumnus Mike Wallace. A book on the school Not Just Any Medical School by Horace Davenport was revised and published for the sesquicentennial. The sesquicentennial office also published Know Thy Place, a compendium of biographies of notable Medical School alumni.
The Sesquicentennial committee involved the students by creating a "day in the life of a medical school student" display. The student were given 33 disposable cameras and told to photograph student life. The sesquicentennial brought together the whole of the Medical School, alumni, faculty, staff, and students, to celebrate its heritage.
For more information on the Medical School, please see the Medical School web site: http://www.med.umich.edu/medschool. For more archival information please see the University of Michigan Medical School finding aid at the Bentley Library.
The records consist of material created and compiled by the staff of the Medical School Sesquicentennial Office. The records include a variety of information about the planning and production of special events, and publications and publicity for the 150-year anniversary of the Medical School.
The collection is divided into eight series: Sesquicentennial Committee Materials, Publicity, Exhibits and Displays, Events, Audio-Visual, Publications, and Artifacts.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Medical School Sesquicentennial Office.; University of Michigan. Medical School--History.; University of Michigan--Anniversaries, etc.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
University of Michigan. Medical School Sesquicentennial Office.; University of Michigan. Medical School--History.; University of Michigan--Anniversaries, etc.; University of Michigan. Medical School--Students.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Photonegatives.; Videotapes.
- Sesquicentennial Committee Materials
  The records of the Sesquicentennial Committee contain a planning guide, a calendar of events, meeting minutes, correspondence and information about department involvement in the celebration.
  - Planning Guide 1998 (Box 1)
  - Calendar of Events 1999 (Box 1)
  - Committee Minutes 2000 (Box 1)
  - Committee Minutes, (including overall plan and chronology of major contributions list) December 1997-1999, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Committee Correspondence, including committee member list and meeting planning information May 1997-October 1998 (Box 1)
  - Planning for Communications and Publicity circa 1998 (Box 1)
  - Jean Horrigan, Event Planning Evaluation Report April 1999 (Box 1)
  - Department Representative Information 1998-1999 (Box 1)
  - Department Event Plans 1999 (Box 1)
- Publicity
  Publicity materials consist of reports from the Public Relations firm, informational media kits, and numerous clippings from publications and articles about the Medical School Sesquicentennial from a variety of journals, newsletters and newspapers, and planning materials for multiple exhibits and displays on campus.
  - Public Relations
    - United States Congressional Record, 1999 (oversize folder) (Box 1)
    - University Medical Center Media Release Package 2000 (Box 1)
    - Publicity Firm Proposals, Franco Public Relations Firm Meetings and Memos August 1998-November 1999 (Box 1)
    - Publicity Planning: Convocation Strategy August 1998-December 1999 (Box 1)
    - Franco Public Relations Report on Newspaper Coverage March 2000-July 2000 (Box 1)
    - Franco Public Relations Correspondence, Monthly Reports, and Clippings December 1998-February 2000 (Box 1)
    - Media Releases, Notes and Clippings 1999 (Box 1)
    - Sesquicentennial Media Kit, includes committee list, dean list and speaker biographies 1999 (Box 1)
  - Clippings and Articles
    - Clippings and Printed Materials September 1999-August 2000, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor News clippings, and correspondence with Dave Whalberg, Ann Arbor News, June 1998-September 1999 (Box 1)
    - Messenger (Medical School Staff Newsletter), August 1999-December 2000 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Daily clippings, September 1999-February 2000 (Box 1)
    - University Record clippings, July 1999-February 2000 (Box 1)
  - Brochures, Mailings and Merchandising
    - Design of Sesquicentennial Logo and Stationery 1999 (Box 1)
    - Brochures, Invitations and Mailings 1998-1999 (Box 1)
    - Sesquicentennial Events Flyers 1999 (Box 1)
    - Merchandising 1999-2000 (see also Artifacts series) (Box 1)
- Exhibits and Displays
  The Sesquicentennial included several exhibits and displays in the Medical Center, on the university campus and at the University of Michigan Art Museum. The records include information about the development, planning, research, location and presentation of the exhibits and displays.
  - Time Line and Alumni Memory Project
    - Web Site Design 1998-1999 (Box 1)
    - Time Line and Poster Design 1998-1999 (Box 1)
    - Time Line Additions from Departments 1999 (Box 1)
    - Department Time Line Posters from Ophthalmology and Physiology circa 1999 (located in oversize folder) (Box 1)
    - Alumni Letters 1998-1999 (Box 1)
    - Memory Lane Project from Alumni Letters 1998-1999 (Box 1)
  - Art Museum Exhibit
    - Medical School Deans Portraits: Proposal for Restoration and Conservation 1997 (Box 1)
    - Art Museum Exhibit Proposal: Seeing is Healing, The Visual Arts of Medicine, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Seeing is Healing, The Visual Arts of Medicine Exhibit Opening and Unveiling of New Medical School Deans Portraits, August 1999-October 2000 (Box 1)
  - Architectural Projects
    - Research about the Possible Reconstruction of the Old Main Hospital Arch at the Medical School 1998 (Box 1)
    - Plans for Historical Building Plaques for Early Medical Building Sites 1999 (Box 1)
  - Exhibits for Display Within the Medical Center
    - Exhibits and Displays Planned for Medical Center Buildings 1998-2000 (Box 1)
    - Proposals for Turn-of-the-century Doctor's Office Display 1999 (Box 1)
    - Class Photograph Preservation and Repair, for Display in Medical Science I Building (includes display layout) 1999 (Box 1)
    - Proposal for Medical Science II Building Mural circa 1999 (located in oversize folder) (Box 1)
    - Medical Center Alumni Society Hall of Honor Display and Brochure 1998-1999 (Box 1)
- Events
  The Medical School community planned a number of events for the Sesquicentennial year, including an opening convocation, an all-alumni reunion, a symposium, various lectures throughout the year, a Medical Center birthday luncheon for the medical school and medical center staff and a final gala celebration to end the sesquicentennial year. The materials contain planning, staffing, coordination and location information on most Sesquicentennial events
  - Regional Alumni Events
    - Field Events Calendar and Brochures 1998-1999 (Box 1)
    - All Alumni Reunion Plan for the Convocation Weekend 1999 (Box 1)
  - Convocation
    - Planning 1999 (Box 1)
    - Convocation Program Planning 1999 (Box 1)
    - Speaker Biographies 1999 (Box 1)
    - Invitation Letters 1999 (Box 1)
    - Confirmation and Thank You Letters 1999 (Box 1)
    - Academic Dress Information and Order 1999 (Box 1)
    - Financial Information 1999 (Box 1)
  - Symposium (Box 2)
    - "Will Professionalism be a Casualty of Modern Medicine?" Symposium Preparation and Brochure 1999-2000 (Box 2)
  - Finale Week
    - Finale Week Planning and Preparations 1999-2000 (Box 2)
    - Medical School Birthday Party Events, including Pfizer Donation of Breakfast for Medical Offices 2000 (Box 2)
    - Sesquicentennial Gala, Final Event Planning and Invitation 1999-2000 (Box 2)
- Publications
  - Journal of the American Medical Association (Volume 283 Number 7), February 2000
    - Journal of the American Medical Association Edition Publicity Poster, 1999 (located in oversize folder) (Box 2)
    - Drafts of Articles for Journal of the American Medical Association University of Michigan Sesquicentennial Issue, circa 1999 (Box 2)
  - Know Thy Place, Megan O. Schimpf, ed., biographies of University of Michigan Medical School Graduates, Sesquicentennial Publication, 2000 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Medicine, Michigan State Medical Society Magazine, Article on Medical School Dean Allen S. Lichter, August-September 2000 (Box 2)
  - Not Just Any Medical School printing and Distribution, 1998-1999 (Box 2)
- Video Production
  - Celebrating 150 Years of Scholarship and Service, University of Michigan Medical School, Video Contract agreement, award applications 1998 (Box 2)
  - Video Research and Box Cover Design 1997-1999 (Box 2)
  - Video Scripts, Mike Wallace Narration 1998 (Box 2)
  - Video Financial 1998-1999 (Box 2)
- Audio-Visual
  The audio-video records contain the Sesquicentennial video that was written and produced about the history of the Medical School, tapes of publicity spots on NBC's Today show, a Detroit Radio Morning show, and a educational CD-ROM from one of the Sesquicentennial committee members. The records include numerous photographs and negatives from disposable cameras given to Medical school students to document daily student life. Artifacts created with the Sesquicentennial logo are included in the record group.
  - Audio-Video
    - Celebrating 150 Years of Scholarship and Service, University of Michigan Medical School Video 1999 (Box 2)
    - "University of Michigan Medical School-150th Anniversary" Today Show Video Tape, NBC Network February 21, 2000 (Box 2)
    - "University of Michigan Medical School-150th Anniversary" The Morning Show II WJR-AM (ABC) Detroit Audio Tape February 16, 2000 (Box 2)
    - Histopathology Sequence: Laboratory Lessons 1-8, CD-ROM, Department of Pathology University of Michigan Medical School, Drs. G.D. Abrams, M.D. Lougee, S.J. Pilon, L.M. Stoolman, April 2000 (Box 2)
  - Photographs
    - Student Life Photographs 1999, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Student Life Negatives 1999 (Box 2)
    - Slides for Presentations 1998 (Box 2)
    - Dr. Antonia Novella in Mott Children's Hospital, University of Michigan alumnae, speaker at convocation, copy print of a 1971 photo (Box 2)
- Artifacts
  - Sesquicentennial Logo Plastic Travel Mug 1999 (Box 2)
  - Sesquicentennial Logo Lapel Pins (two designs) 1999 (Box 2)